Guide to the Jean Louis Berlandier Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jean Louis Berlandier papers
1745-1860
1815-1850
WA MSS S-300
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.76
19 boxes + 1 broadside.
The papers consist of diaries and accounts written or collected by Jean Louis Berlandier, including works by Rafael Chovell, Manuel de Mier y Teran, José Francisco Ruiz, Stephen F. Austin, Juan Pedro Walker and others. The papers include maps, letters, diaries, histories, and government documents containing geographical, ethnographic, and historical information about the Mexican Republic, particularly the region between the Sabine River and Sierra Madre, with extensive coverage of the areas that today comprise Tamaulipas, Nuevo Leon, Cohuila, and Texas.
Berlandier, Jean Louis, -1851
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Henry R. Wagner, 1919; H. P. Kraus, Inc., 1986; and gift of William Reese (Yale 1977), 1993.
Custodial History
The bulk of the material in the papers was originally part of a larger collection purchased in 1853 by Darius Nash Couch in Matamoros, Mexico, later acquired by the English firm of Bernard Quaritch and the collector Sir Thomas Phillipps. Karl Hiersemann of Leipzig purchased most of the Berlandier papers at the Phillipps auctions in 1913 and 1919, Henry R. Wagner purchased them from him, and the library purchased the papers from Wagner in 1919.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions available on microfilm.
Jean Louis Berlandier
Jean Louis Berlandier (circa 1805-1851), French botanist, trained under Cuvier in Paris and Auguste Pyrame de Candolle in Geneva, who sent him to Mexico in 1826 to collect botanical specimens. In 1827, he joined the Mexican Comisión de Limites, an international boundary commission between the United States and Mexico. Berlandier conducted botanical, environmental, and social surveys of the border region for the Comisión. He later settled in Matamoros, where he worked as a doctor. During 1845-1846 he worked as a hospital administrator and, after the American invasion during the Mexican War, 1846-1858, acted as interpreter for the United States Army.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of diaries and accounts written or collected by Jean Louis Berlandier during his travels in Texas and Mexico. The papers include maps, letters, diaries, histories, and government documents containing geographical, ethnographic, and historical information about the Mexican Republic, particularly the region between the Sabine River and Sierra Madre, with extensive coverage of the areas that today comprise Tamaulipas, Nuevo Leon, Coahuila, and Texas. Included in the collection are Juan Pedro Walker's diary of expeditions in 1815-1816 from Monterey into Texas, Jean Louis Berlandier's writings on Mexico, and letters from Manuel Gayasos de Lemos to William Dunbar concerning the Florida border. Other writers include Rafael Chovell, José Francisco Ruiz, and Manuel de Mier y Teran.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Henry R. Wagner Berlandier Papers, 1745-1860. II. Materials Purchased from H. P. Kraus, Inc., 1826-1844. III. Material Donated by William S. Reese, circa 1850. IV. Miscellaneous Berlandier Manuscripts, 1827-1849. Series correspond to acquisitions.
Researchers should note that material within each acquisition may overlap with or relate to material found in other acquisitions. For instance, diaries from Berlandier's expeditions may be found in multiple acquisitions. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received and cataloged by the library.
General note
Articles describing the collection and its history can be found in The Yale University Library Gazette 31(1957):130-32, 32(1958):71-76.
Botanists -- France; Gutiérrez-Magee Expedition, 1812-1813; Land grants -- Texas; Meteorology -- Mexico; Mexican War, 1846-1848 -- Campaigns; Public officers -- Mexico; Alamo (San Antonio, Tex.) -- Pictorial works; Florida -- Boundaries -- United States; Galveston Bay (Tex.); Matamoros (Tamaulipas, Mexico) -- Statistics, Medical; Mexico -- Gazetteers; Mexico -- Maps; Mexico -- Description and travel; Mexico -- History -- 1810-; Mexico -- History -- 1821-1861; Mexico -- History -- To 1810; New Spain -- Maps; Nuevo León (Mexico: State) -- Pictorial works; Provincias Internas (New Spain); San Antonio (Tex.); Tamaulipas (Mexico) -- Pictorial works; Texas -- Maps; Texas -- Boundaries -- United States; Texas -- Description and travel; Texas -- History -- To 1846; Texas -- Politics and government -- To 1846; United States -- Boundaries -- Florida; United States -- Boundaries -- Texas; Diaries -- France -- 19th century; Diaries -- Mexico -- 19th century; Drawings (visual works) -- Mexico -- 19th century; Maps (documents) -- Mexico -- 19th century; Botanists -- France -- 19th century; Public officers -- Mexico -- 19th century; Almonte, Juan Nepomuceno, 1803-1869; Austin, Stephen F. (Stephen Fuller), 1793-1836; Berlandier, Jean Louis, -1851; Chovell, Rafael; Dunbar, William, 1749-1810; García, Diego Martin; Gayoso de Lemos, Manuel, 1747-1799; Mier y Teran, Manuel de; Músquiz, Ramón, approximately 1797-; Ruíz, José Francisco, 1783-1840; Toqui, Juan Bautista; Villareal, José M.; Wagner, Henry R. (Henry Raup), 1862-1957; Walker, Juan Pedro; Mexico. Comisión de Límites
- Henry R. Wagner Berlandier Papers, 1745-1860; Series I
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged in the order in which it was originally cataloged by the library.
  Scope and Contents
  This portion of the collection contains diaries, ledgers, maps, and drawings primarily created or collected by Jean Louis Berlandier and the Mexican Comision de Limites in Texas and Mexico from 1826-1860. This material provides geographical, ethnographic, historical, and visual documentation of the Mexican Republic and the Mexican-American War. The series also includes a twenty volume set titled "Gazetteer of Mexico," with entries for Mexican and Texan pueblos and cities.
  - Berlandier, Gazetteer of Mexico, circa 1840-1860; 2.71; 7 boxes
    Twenty autograph manuscript volumes of a geographical index of Mexico. Includes information on the location of pueblos and cities, as well as information on their government, inhabitants, languages spoken, and climate. Areas surveyed include Cuernevaca, San Miguel, Veracruz, Oaxaca, Coahuila, and Nuevo Leon. There is also an extensive entry for Goliad, Texas present in volume 9. The title of the series is taken from the labels on spines, apparently affixed by Sir Thomas Phillipps.
    - Gazetteer of Mexico, circa 1840-1860 (Box 1)
    - Gazetteer of Mexico, circa 1840-1860 (Box 2)
    - Gazetteer of Mexico, circa 1840-1860 (Box 3)
    - Gazetteer of Mexico, circa 1840-1860 (Box 4)
    - Gazetteer of Mexico, circa 1840-1860 (Box 5)
    - Gazetteer of Mexico, circa 1840-1860 (Box 6)
    - Gazetteer of Mexico, circa 1840-1860 (Box 7)
  - Berlandier, Voyage au Mexique, Année 1826, 1 (Box 8)
    Autograph manuscript journal of a trip from Havre de Grace, Maryland to Tampico, Mexico. Includes "Observations physiques" of ocean location and travel on pages 123-188.
    Custodial History
    Phillipps number 15475
  - Berlandier, Voyage au Mexique: Itineraires, ports, cotes, baies, etc. de la Republique Mexicaine, circa 1855 (Box 8)
    Two volumes containing approximately 38 maps and plans of the Gulf of Mexico, Tampico, Bexar, and other Mexican areas, apparently made for the Comision des Limites.
    Phillipps number 16485
  - Berlandier, Voyage au Mexique: Vues, circa 1830; 1 (Box 9)
    25 ink drawings of views and plans of various areas in Mexico, including Chapultepec Castle, San Luis Potosí, and Goliad, Texas. Accompanied by a letter, apparently signed by Berlandier.
    Phillipps number 16545
  - Berlandier, Pencil and ink drawings and maps of Tampico, Nuevo Leon, Coahuila y Texas, and other Mexican areas, undated (Box 8)
    Phillipps number 16454
  - Berlandier, Diario, 1831; 1 (Box 10)
    Autograph manuscript diary containing meteorological observations.
    Phillipps number 20747
  - Berlandier, Voyage de Matamoros a Goliad, Bexar, Rio Grande, etc., [1834]; 1 (Box 10)
    Two incomplete portions of a manuscript diary documenting an 1834 journey from Matamoros to Goliad and an 1834 trip from Bexar to the Rio Grande. Includes three maps of rivers, including the Rio de Medina.
    Phillipps number 24069
  - Journal and notes on a trip from Mexico to Texas (Box 10)
    The following are bound together in one volume, and are listed in alphabetical, rather than actual, order.
    Phillipps number 15477
    - Berlandier, Note des Observations a Faire dans les Voyages, 1827-1828 (Box 10)
      Manuscript journal containing geological and biological observations, including a section titled Aspect Botanico-Agricole de la Route de Mexico à Saint Luis Potosi, 1827 December.
    - Mexico. Comision de limites
      - Diary of the journey from Mexico to the Trinity River, Texas, 1827 November 10-1828 May 24 (Box 10)
        According to Wagner, this diary may have been kept by Manuel Mier y Teran.
      - Diary of the journey from Mexico to the Trinity River, Texas, 1827 November 10-1828 June 18 (Box 10)
        According to Wagner, this diary was kept by Rafael Chovell.
  - Berlandier, Antiquities found in the ruins of Tula, Tamaulipas, undated (Box 11)
    12 drawings of Indian sculptures and artifacts
    Phillipps number 16455
  - Berlandier, Planos topograficos de diferentes fortificaciones, etc., 1829-1846 (Box 11)
    48 maps and plans of fortifications, including fortifications in Texas.
    Phillipps number 34450
  - Notebook concerning the Mexican-American War (Box 11)
    Phillipps number 15587
    - Berlandier, Jean Louis
      - Autograph letter, signed, to General Francisco Mejía, from Matamoros, Mexico, 1846 March 1 (Box 11)
        Docketed: Apuntes para la formacion de los mapas militares de las imediaciones de Matamoros.
      - Reconocimiento de las Principales Labores Imediatas a la Villa de Ampudia, Matamoros, 1846 March 10 (Box 11)
        Signed L. B. [Louis Berlandier]
      - Itinerario: Campana de Palo Alto y Resaca de Guerrero, [1846] (Box 11)
        Covers operations from 1846 March 10-June 12.
      - Estracto de un diario escrito durante la ocupacion de Matamoros por las tropas Americanos, [1846] (Box 11)
        Related Materials
        See also: "Estracto de un diario escrito durante la ocupacion de Matamoros por las tropas Americanos," Box 14. Possibly written by Berlandier.
      - Report from Matamoros, transmitting information on United States forces at Corpus Christi, 1846 March 23 (Box 11)
        The name of the informant was inked out but may have been Briol.
      - Report of the advantages of the Sierra San Carlos, Tamaulipas, as a theater of military operations, Matehuala, 1847 January 27 (Box 11)
    - Briol, Declaration on United States forces at Corpus Christi, [1846] (Box 11)
    - Hamilton, Fowler, Statement on the reason for the American advance to the Rio Grande, [1846] March 15 (Box 11)
      Signed by F. Hamilton, 2d Dragoons.
    - Toqui, Juan Bautista, Autograph letter, signed, to Berlandier from Matamoros, Mexico, 1846 March 16 (Box 11)
    - Villareal, José M.
      - Report on United States forces at Corpus Christi, [1846] (Box 11)
      - Summary of his information on American forces at Corpus Christi, 1846 (Box 11)
    - [Toqui, Juan Bautista,] Two autograph letters, signed with a cross, to Berlandier, concerning information on United States forces in Texas, [1846] (Box 11)
  - Mexico, Comision de limites, Journal de voyage aux limites N.E. de la republique mexicaine, par ordre du Congres de l'union, sous la direction du General Manuel de Mier y Teran, undated (Box 12)
    Travel journal and astronomical observations.
    Phillipps number 15501
  - Notebook by Berlandier and the Comision de Limites (Box 12)
    Phillipps number 21674
    - [Berlandier, Jean Louis]
      - Notas Sobre la Revolucion de Mexico, undated (Box 12)
        Probably compiled by J. L. Berlandier.
      - Notas para Servir a la Historia de la Provincias Internas, undated (Box 12)
        Notes on the divisions and governance of the province, including the Spanish Indian Policy. Probably compiled by Berlandier.
    - Mexico, Comision de limites, Adiciones y Correcciones a los Diarios de Viaje, undated (Box 12)
      Relates to Indians in Texas, American settlers, forest conservation, and related matters. Possibly written by Teran.
  - Mexico. Comision de limites. Texas Por Teran: Su Viaje 1828-29, [1828 April 13 - 1829 March 7] (Box 12)
    Manuscript diary in an unidentified hand concerning Manuel Mier y Teran's journey to Texas in 1828-1829. The diary contains descriptions of Indians and governmental relations between Mexico and the United States.
  - Mexico. Comision de limites. Journal de Voyage de la Commission de limites de la Republique Mexicaine, aux ordres de S. E. le General de Division Manuel de Mier y Teran, 1827 November 10 - 1828 August 13 (Box 12)
    Manuscript diary, possibly in the hand of Manuel Mier y Teran, covering an expedition to Nacogdoches, two excursions to the Sabine, and an expedition to the coast of Tamaulipas.
    Phillipps number 15467
  - Mexico. Comision de limites. Diario de Viage de la Comision de limites a las Fronteras N.E. de la Republica Mexicana y en varios estados de la federacion, [1827-1828] (Box 13)
    Part 1 covers 1827 November 29 - 1828 June 2. The other 4 parts cover 1827 November 10 - 1828 December 14.
    Phillipps number 15465
  - Mexico. Comision de limites. Diario de Viage de la Comision de limites a las Fronteras N.E. de la Republica Mexicana y en varios estados de la federacion. Maps., undated; 1; folder (Broadside) (Box 13, Folder 14 (Broadside))
  - Berlandier and Chovell notebook (Box 13)
    - [Berlandier, Jean Louis], compiler
      - Historia: notes on phases of Mexican history, undated (Box 13)
        Includes notes on viceroys of Mexico; Mexican revolutions; the revolution of the negroes, 1634; the Inquisition; the Mexican councils; printing in Mexico; and mines. Also includes a table of exports from Mexico, 1826-1828.
        Phillipps number 15504
      - Texas: Statistical and descriptive notes from various sources, undated (Box 13)
        Partial contents include: Villa de Goliad [R. Chovell]; Estadistica de Tejas por el Cd. Almonte, 1834; Censo y Estadistica. Departamento de Bejar, 1832 [Ramon Musquiz]; Censo y estadistica. Departamento de Bejar, 1831 [R. Musquiz]; Rivières du Texas; De l'agriculture des environs de Bejar; Campaña de Texas.
        Phillipps number 15500
    - Chovell, Rafael
      - Apuntes Sobre el Viaje desde Goliad a Matamoros Pasanda por Bejar, Rio Grande, y las Villas del Norte, 1834 May 26 - July 27 (Box 13)
      - Catalogo de las Rochas Tomadas en los Caminos de Bejar a Rio Grande (villa Guerrero) y de este a Matamoros, undated (Box 13)
  - [Chovell, Rafael], Considerations Generales sur le Departement de Texas, undated (Box 13)
    Discusses the geography, topography, agriculture, cattle, missions, and Mexican settlements of Texas. Also discusses the Austin Colony and the DeWitt Colony, particularly their commerce and slaves.
    Phillipps number 15594
  - Notebook on Texas (Box 15)
    - Conduite d'Elizondo et du General Arredondo après la Bataille de Medina., undated (Box 15)
    - Mier y Teran, Manuel de, Apuntes relativos a las colonias de Texas en el año de 1830 (Box 15)
    - Marin, Primo Feliciano, Visite de l'Eveque du Nouveau Leon au Texas en 1805 - Volcan d'air en Sicile - Samogite, undated (Box 15)
      Possibly compiled by Rafael Chovell. Bishop Marin's account was published in 1830 as Supplement No. 4 of Voz de la Patria. Cf. Streeter, Bibliography of Texas, No. 758.
    - Notes sur la premiere Revolucion de Texas, 1813 (Box 15)
    - Notes sur la Revolucion de Texas en 1813, fournis par une femme de Bejar, victime des exces des royalistes Espagnols, undated (Box 15)
    - Reparticion de terras en Tejas hasta 1830, undated (Box 15)
    - Rodriguez, J. M., Notes du cure Dn. J. M. Rodriguez sur l'invasion des Insurges du Texas l'année 1812 et celle de 1813, undated (Box 15)
    - Sanchez, José María, Fenomeno: An account of "water witching" at Nacogdoches, Texas, 1828 June 23 (Box 15)
    - Saucedo, José Antonio, Autograph letter, signed, to Victor Blanco, Vice Gobernador of Coahuila and Texas, from Bexar, Texas, 1826 September 3 (Box 15)
      States that George Orr has been elected alcalde of Atascocito and requests confirmation in his office
    - Wilkinson à la Frontière du Texas en 1806: Notes on the movements of United States and Spanish troops during the boundary dispute, undated (Box 15)
  - [Chovell, Rafael?], Extraits d'astronomie nautique et de quelques considerations sur les moyens dont se servent les marins de leur art, undated (Box 15)
    Ascribed to Chovell by Thomas W. Streeter.
    Phillipps number 15473
  - [Chovell, Rafael], Journal of scientific observations made in Venezuela, [after 1803] (Box 15)
    The first 16 pages contain outlines of general research topics under the headings "Des recherches physiques et chimiques sur les eaux," "Autres recherches sur les eaux," "Recherches météorologiques," "Sur l'électricité atmosphérique," "Physique," and "Considérations géologiques." The second part is divided into four sections labelled "Chapitre VII," "Chapitre VIII," "Livre IV," "Chapitre X" and "Chapitre XI," and contains detailed notes on geology, meteorology, natural history, and other scientific observations made while traveling in Venezuela.
    Phillipps number 15472
  - [Berlandier], Estracto de un diario escrito durante la ocupacion de Matamoros por las tropas Americanos, 1846 May 17-21 (Box 15)
    See also: "Estracto de un diario escrito durante la ocupacion de Matamoros por las tropas Americanos," Box 11. Possibly written by Berlandier.
    Phillipps number 15526
  - Rivera y Villalon, Pedro de, Journal du General de Brigade Don Pedro Rivera, ecrit durant sa visite des provinces internes du Mexique, undated (Box 15)
    Published in Guatemala, 1736, with the title Diario y Derrotero. Includes notes on his travels to the presidios of the Provincias Internas, Nuevo Toledo, Nueva Galicia, Nuevo Mexico, Nuevas Filipinas, Nuevo Leon, and Texas.
    Phillipps number 15591
  - Ruiz, José Francisco, Relacion que Manifiesta las Observaciones y Adiciones que Hace el que Avajo se Suscrive Sobre la Noticia de las Diferentes Tribus de Salvajes Conocidos que Havitan en el Departamento de Tejas, undated (Box 16)
    Manuscript volume containing information on Indian tribes in Texas, particularly the Comanche.
    Phillipps number 15482
  - Garcia, Diego Martin, Breve y Legal Noticia de las Calidades y Costumbres de los Indios: Metodo que han de observar con ellos, y consigo mismos: los obreros evangelicos que quieren ganar sus alma para Dios. Escrita por el P. F. Diego Martin Garcia, predicador apolstolico, hijo del seminario de propaganda side de la ssma. Cruz de Queretaro., 1745 (Box 16)
    Manuscript volume, signed by Diego Martin Garcia, on the qualities and customs of Indian tribes, particularly pertaining to efforts to convert them to Christianity.
  - Notebook on Texas and the Austin Colony (Box 16)
    Phillipps number 15458
    - Anahuac, Texas, Committee of Vigilance, Al Pueblo de Esta Jurisdiccion, 1832 June 21 (Box 16)
      Manifesto in favor of Santa Anna, signed by John Austin, Henry Smith and others, together with an account of the rising at Anahuac, apparently written for L'Abeille, New Orleans.
    - Apuntos Relativos a la Colonia de Austin, formados en el mes de Junio de 1828, [1828 June] (Box 16)
      Notes on Moses and Stephen F. Austin, including their colonization attempts and their contract with the Baron de Bastrop.
    - Fisher, George, Four autograph letters, signed, to Manuel Mier y Teran from Anahuac, Texas, 1832 January 8-13 (Box 16)
      On customs administration in Texas; discusses the difficulty of being opposed by the Austin colonists and not supported by Mexican officials.
    - Mier y Teran, Manuel de, Letterbook containing letters to General Teran and copies of letters written by him, mainly concerning political affairs in Texas, 1828-1832 (Box 16)
    - Austin, Stephen Fuller, Five autograph letters, signed, to Manuel Mier y Teran from Austin, Texas, 1828 May-September (Box 16)
      Discussing the Austin Colony's climate, industry, and trade, particularly in cotton and slaves.
    - Mier y Teran, Manuel de
      - Autograph letter to Felipe de la Garza from Matamoros, Mexico, 1830 March 2 (Box 16)
        Concerning affairs in Texas, particularly Mier y Teran's feeling of helpless and lack of aid from customs officers.
      - Two autograph letters, signed, to José Batres from Nacogdoches, Texas, 1828 July-August (Box 16)
      - Autograph letter to Guadalupe Victoria from Bexar, Texas, 1828 March 28 (Box 16)
        Concerning affairs in Texas; includes a description of Texas, its extent, population, local Indians, the Austin Colony, the Mexican population in Texas, and recommendations for action in Texas. Notes that if the Americans are permitted to own slaves, Mexicans should have the same privilege.
      - Autograph letter to Vicente Guerrero from Matamoros, Mexico, 1829 July 23 (Box 16)
        Concerning affairs in Texas; advises Guerrero to ask Congress to send 10,000 Mexican families to colonize Texas.
      - Lista de los Libros y Cuadernos que Cita El Padre Puelles en su Memoria o Informe Impresa en Zacatecas, undated (Box 16)
    - Tarnava, Constantino de, Copy of letter to Ministro de Guerra y Marina from Mexico, 1830 January 7 (Box 16)
      Gives General Teran's view on affairs in Texas.
  - Notebook on Mexico and Texas (Box 16)
    - Azcárate y Lezama, Juan Francisco, Voto del que Suscribe Cómo Individuo de la Junta de Limites Sre. las Tres Preguntas Propestas por el Gobo, 1827 October 5 (Box 16)
      Signed: Mexico, Juan Franc. de Azcarate. Es copia, Mexico, Oct 5 de 1827. J. M. Duran.
    - Berlandier, Jean Louis
      - Itinerario a Bexar desde Durango, undated (Box 16)
        On verso: "Couvents et missions de la province de Zacatecas."
      - Histoire: Notes Pour Servir á l'Histoire de la Revolution de la Nouvelle Espagne, undated (Box 16)
      - Principales Epoques de l'Histoire Mexicaine, avec une Courte Description des Localites qui en Furent le Théâtre, undated (Box 16)
      - Tamaulipas: Notes on the coast lands between Matamoros and Refugio, undated (Box 16)
    - Mexico (Viceroyalty)
      - Texas, Autos de Revilla Gigedo: Copy of proceedings of a Junta de guerra y hacienda in 1754 relative to French encroachments in Texas, undated (Box 16)
        Copy of proceedings of a Junta de guerra y hacienda in 1754 relative to French encroachments in Texas.
      - Testimonio del Espediente ... Sobre Investigar los Verdaderos Limites de la Provincia de Texas, 1816 (Box 16)
        2 copies made for the Comision de limites.
    - Mexico, Comision de limites
      - Recapitulacion de los Hechos que han Precedido al Tratado de Sr. Onis con Respecto a la Frontera Mexicana., 1828 April 8 (Box 16)
        From San Antonio de Bexar. Possibly in Manuel de Mier y Teran's handwriting.
      - Sketched map of the Texas boundary in the vincinity of Nacogdoches, undated (Box 16)
      - Texas, Bahia de Galveston, undated (Box 16)
        Possibly in Manuel de Mier y Teran's hand.
    - Mier y Teran, Manuel de, Apuntes para la Comision de limites, 1827 October 26 (Box 16)